Adams family papers
Litchfield Historical Society
Adams family papers
1798-1928
1798-1877
Litchfield Historical Society 7 South Street, P.O. Box 385 Litchfield, CT, 6759 URL: http://www.litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org/archon Email: archivist@litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org Phone: 860-567-4501 Fax: 860-567-3565
Adams, Charles, 1805-1883; Adams, Charles, Jr., 1845-1864; Adams, Joseph, 1764-1856; Wessells, Julia Adams How, 1842-1904; Wheelock, Mary Adams, 1838-1895
2.00
The personal papers of the Adams Family, including Joseph Adams (1767-1856); his son, Charles Adams (1805-1883); children of Charles Adams, including Julia Adams How Wessells (1842-1904), Mary Adams Wheelock (1838-1895), and Charles Adams Jr. (1845-1864); other family members; and friends and business associates. The collection consists primarily of correspondence.
1970-35-1
Biographical Note
Charles Adams (1805-1883) was a son of Litchfield residents Joseph Adams (1764-1856) and Deborah Marsh Adams (1773-1857). In the early 1820s, Charles Adams moved to New Haven and apprenticed with the printer Thomas Collier, formerly of Litchfield, and worked in the office of Sherman Converse. Adams established a printing business in 1825 and published The New Haven Chronicle in 1827 and then founded the New Haven Palladium in 1829. In the early 1830s, he moved to Bath, N.Y., where he published The Constitutionalist beginning in 1834. He also published the Corning and Blossburg Advocate. When his brother Henry died unexpectedly in 1842, Adams moved back to Litchfield and continued publication of The Litchfield Enquirer until 1845, when it was sold to Payne Kilbourne. Twice Adams assumed the editorship of the paper until it was sold to James Humphrey in 1859. After 1845, Adams was elected judge of probate court, a position he held for fourteen of the next twenty years. He was a deacon of the Congregational Church; a director of the Litchfield Savings Bank, the Litchfield Female Academy, and the Litchfield County Historical and Antiquarian Society, and a member of the Board of Visitors of the Elm Park Collegiate Institute. He married Jane Hinman of New Haven in 1827. She died in 1828. He married Julia Hinman of New Haven in 1830 and they had ten children.
Scope and Contents
The personal papers of the Adams Family, including Joseph Adams (1767-1856); his son, Charles Adams (1805-1883); children of Charles Adams, including Julia Adams How Wessells (1842-1904), Mary Adams Wheelock (1838-1895), and Charles Adams Jr. (1845-1864); other family members; and friends and business associates. The collection consists primarily of correspondence.
Family members were descendants of Henry Adams of Braintree and distant cousins of the famous Adams family of Massachusetts. Joseph Adams was a fourth cousin of President John Quincy Adams. Living contemporaneously in Litchfield was the family of Judge Andrew Adams (1736-1797), which descended from Samuel Adams of Stratford, Conn., and not related to the family of Joseph Adams.
Joseph Adams moved to Litchfield from Roxbury, Mass., in 1790 and established himself as a cabinet maker. With advertisements in issues of the Litchfield Monitor for June 1790 he introduced himself to Litchfield residents as a cabinet maker from Boston and solicited their business. He advertised frequently in the 1790s for apprentices, but sold his shop in 1802. He was Litchfield borough clerk, 1818-1823 and 1824-1838 and borough president 1839-1842. He also served as constable for six years, lister or rate-maker (functioning as assessor) for twelve years, grand juror for six years, a director of the Litchfield Savings Bank, and a surveyor. He married Deborah Marsh in 1792 and they had eight children.
Two of the children, Henry Adams (1794-1842) and Charles Adams (1805-1883), established themselves in the newspaper business. The early interest of Joseph in journalism is evidenced in a letter he received from his nephew, Charles Chauncey Adams (1788-1814) in 1807, in which he acknowledges information regarding the status of newspapers published in Litchfield. After working in Huntsville, Ala., in the 1820s, where he was associated with newspapers there, Henry Adams purchased the Litchfield County Post in 1829, changing the title to The Litchfield Enquirer with his first issue, January 29, 1829. He continued to publish the newspaper until his death by accidental drowning in 1842.
In the early 1820s, Charles Adams moved to New Haven and apprenticed with the printer Thomas Collier, formerly of Litchfield, and worked in the office of Sherman Converse. Adams established a printing business in 1825 and published The New Haven Chronicle in 1827 and then founded the New Haven Palladium in 1829. In the early 1830s, he moved to Bath, N.Y., where he published The Constitutionalist beginning in 1834. He also published the Corning and Blossburg Advocate. When his brother Henry died unexpectedly in 1842, Adams returned to Litchfield and continued publication of The Litchfield Enquirer until 1845, when it was sold to Payne Kilbourne. Twice Adams assumed editorship of the paper until it was sold to James Humphrey in 1859. After 1845, Adams was elected judge of probate court, a position he held for fourteen of the next twenty years. He was a deacon of the Congregational Church; a director of the Litchfield Savings Bank, the Litchfield Female Academy, and the Litchfield County Historical and Antiquarian Society, and a member of the Board of Visitors of the Elm Park Collegiate Institute.
With the exceptions of Henry Adams and Charles Adams (who returned from Bath, N.Y.), all of the children of Joseph and Deborah Marsh Adams left Litchfield: Sarah Adams Peck (1792-1877) to Bristol, Conn.; Betsey Adams May (1796-1877) to Bath, N.Y.; Amos Adams (1798-1859) to Baton Rouge, La.; John Marsh Adams (1801-1853) to Augusta, Ga.; Kezia Adams Rogers (1811-1899) to Buffalo; and Thomas William (1814-1848), to Augusta, Ga.
The collection consists primarily of correspondence received by Joseph Adams from family members and members of the Litchfield community with legal or other matters involving him and correspondence among the immediate members of the family of Charles Adams, in particular, two daughters of Charles Adams, Mary Adams Wheelock and Julia Adams How Wessells. The correspondence is mostly personal in nature, relating to family news and concerned with matters of health, births, deaths, and visits. This was a traveling family, all generations, so there is an occasional glimpse glimpse of the trials of stage and canal travel. There is a pervasive religious awareness in the letters, perhaps most expressed by Charles to his father in the 1820s. Unfortunately, there is nothing in the collection related to the early career of Joseph Adams as a cabinet maker nor of publishing activities of Henry Adams and Charles Adams in Litchfield.
Although domestic topics predominate in the letters, correspondents sometimes address local or national topics of interest. Joseph's correspondence includes letters from or news about two men who were at one time or another leading business figures in Boston: Amos Lawrence (1786-1852), who was married to Joseph's niece, and Giles Richards (1754-1829), who was Joseph's brother-in-law. For example, Lawrence's 1845 Feb 1 letter offers a personal philosophical expression of a wealthy and successful merchant. Letters from members of the family who moved to the South, particularly from Amos Adams (who owned a plantation and slaves), have a few references to business conditions. A nephew of Joseph Adams, Henry Adams Bullard, wrote twice (1832-1833) to Joseph from Washington when he was a Congressman. Benjamin Tallmadge (1754-1835), another Congressman, wrote Joseph five letters (1814-1826) from Washington, where he was acting for Joseph in financial matters. Four of the letters written while Tallmadge was serving in the House of Representatives.
Some of the papers relate to the Civil War. Charles Adams (1845-1864), the son of Charles and Julia Hinman Adams, enlisted in the 19th Regiment Connecticut Volunteers in 1862 following the outbreak of the Civil War. On June 11, 1864, he died of wounds received on June 1 during the Battle of Cold Harbor. During the war, Adams regularly wrote letters to his parents and sisters. He recorded his thoughts about Generals McClellan, Burnside, and Grant, and President Lincoln; life in camp (maintaining and outfitting tents, sleeping arrangements, food, prayer meetings, entertainments and lectures, snowball battles); support for the Emancipation Proclamation; his belief in the cause; postings, guard duty, inspections, and drills; encouraging enlistment; speculation about duration of war and upcoming military activities; his cousin, Charles Hinman Graves, and other relatives he sees; the 40th N.Y. and Bull Run; African-American dock and government stores workers; guarding “contrabands” (freed or former slaves) from Virginia and Maryland; news of other Litchfield residents; politics in Connecticut; and the weather. The collection contains letters written relative to his death by Representative John H. Hubbard and Marie Barton Greene, who served with the Sanitary Commission. Charles Adams Jr. is not the only Adams family member serving in the Civil War to be documented in the collection; correspondence from Anna Adams (1814-1906) relates to the death of her brother Joseph Henry Adams (1843-1861) during battle on Santa Rosa Island, Fla.
Arrangement of Materials
The collection is arranged in four series:
1. Correspondence
2. Other papers
3. Photographs
4. Albums
Related Materials
Adams family collection (2010-119-0)
Photographs of some Adams family are in Photographs, Portraits: Adams and Baldwin files.
Louisiana State University Libraries, Special Collections. Freemasons St. James Lodge No. 47 (Baton Rouge, La.) records (Mss 2860).
Massachusetts Historical Society
Amos Lawrence Papers.
Separated Materials
Four silhouettes cut from paper (two portraits on one sheet and two on two separate sheets) have been removed from the Adams Family Collection and added to the museum collections.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Family Name:
Adams family
Genre/Form of Material:
Autograph albums; Business records; Correspondence; Photographs
Geographic Name:
Litchfield (Conn.) -- History; United States--Politics and government--1783-1865; United States--Social life and customs--1783-1865
Topical Term:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Alternate Formats Available
Transcriptions are available for some documents.
Additional information is avaliable at http://www.litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Litchfield Historical Society from Margaret and Dorothy Baldwin on 06/01/1970.
Other Information
This collection was processed with support from the Council on Library and Information Resources (CLIR).
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by creator, except for correspondence sent to an Adams family member by a person outside the Adams family, which has been placed in the sub-series for that family member. Item descriptions note major topics of discussion.
  - Abbot, J. B.
    - Abbott, J. B., 1864 Jun 11 (Folder 1)
      Letter to J. H. Hubbard reporting that Charles Adams (1845-1864) has been wounded during the Civil War in battle and is "in a dying condition."
  - Adams, Amos (1798-1859)
    Amos Adams was born in Litchfield and settled in Baton Rouge, La. He was the son of Joseph and Deborah Marsh Adams.
    - Adams, Amos, 1821-1822 (Folder 1)
      Two letters written in Bath, N.Y., to his parents.
      - Adams, Amos to Adams, Joseph and Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1821 Aug 12 (Folder 1)
        Amos reports from Bath, N.Y., on the health of family members and friends and his business affairs.
      - Adams, Amos to Adams, Joseph and Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1822 Jan 19 (Folder 1)
        Amos reports from Bath, N.Y., on family news, birth of his daughter, his father's business dealings, and New York elections.
    - Adams, Amos, 1834-1849 (Folder 2)
      Three letters to his wife and parents.
      - Adams, Amos to Adams, Clara Bailey, 1834 Aug 9 (Folder 2, Folder 1)
        Amos writes that he is eager to receive word from his wife, he misses her and his children, and that he "has not assumed my place in the church."
      - Adams, Amos to Adams, Joseph and Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1843 Apr 13 (Folder 2)
        Amos reports from Baton Rouge on the birth of his son, additional family news, his business of planting cotton, Miller's preaching in the north, and politics.
      - Adams, Amos to Adams, Joseph, 1849 July 28 (Folder 2)
        Amos writes in Baton Rouge that although he might like to, his family and he can not move to Litchfield because his wife and children are natives of Louisiana. He also writes of family news.
    - Adams, Amos, 1858-1859 (Folder 3)
      Two letters written in Baton Rouge to his brother Charles.
      - Adams, Amos to Adams, Charles, 1858 May 8 (Folder 3)
        Amos writes about the condition of the river, family visits and news, Charles's election as probate judge, the Kansas question and slavery, death of his sister-in-law on the packet boat, Sultan.
      - Adams, Amos to Adams, Charles, 1859 Jun 6 (Folder 3)
        Amos writes about family news and health, that he would like to make Litchfield his summer home, and old age.
  - Adams, Anna (1814-1906)
    Anna (Annie) Adams (1814-1906) was the daughter of John Marsh and Sarah (MacMurphy) Adams and was the granddaghter of Joseph and Deborah (Marsh) Adams. She lived in Georgia.
    - Adams, Anna to Adams, Charles, 1861 Oct 16 (Folder 1)
      Five items sent to her uncle related to the death of Anna's brother Joseph Henry Adams (1843-1861), killed during the Civil War in battle on Santa Rosa Island, Fla.: her letter, "To the memory of Joseph H. Adams by one of his playmates," "In memoriam," a newspaper obituary, and the poem "Pensacola."
  - Adams, Charles (1805-1883)
    Charles Adams (1805-1883) was born in Litchfield and eventually settled there. He was the son of Joseph and Deborah (Marsh) Adams. For additional information, see his entry in Creators.
    - Adams, Charles, circa 1810s (Folder 1)
      Two letters written in Sharon, Conn., to his parents. He writes about his visit to Poughkeepsie with Mr. and Mrs. Pierce and that he does not like Mr. Pierce.
    - Adams, Charles, 1822-1826 (Folder 2)
      Four letters written in New Haven, Conn.
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Joseph and Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1822 Nov 22 (Folder 2)
        Charles writes about his decision to join the Church of Christ and mentions Mr. Converse and the office staff as being members of that church. He asks that two religious books be sent to him.
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Kezia, 1825 Aug 29 (Folder 2)
        Charles writes to his sister in detail about the death of a little girl "whom you formerly knew" and "much esteemed," Ann Eliza Starr, who found comfort in her religion at the time of her illness and death.
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Joseph and Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1825 Sep 13 (Folder 2)
        Charles writes about his affection for his parents, his health, his religious feelings and convictions, a speech by Mr. Gould and comments on his alcoholism, and a poem delivered by Dr. Percival.
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Joseph, 1826 Oct 10 (Folder 2)
        Charles inquires about family members. His business is well, but he needs cash, and discusses loans. He believes he is well situated in New Haven and feels attached to the city.
    - Adams, Charles, 1838-1863 (Folder 3)
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Joseph and Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1838 Jan 29 (Folder 3)
        Charles writes about the birth of his daughter, Mary Fairchild, family health and news, and the death of Julius Deming.
      - Adams, Charles to unnamed daughter and May, Betsey Adams, 1853 May 15 (Folder 3)
        Charles writes to a daughter in Bath, N.Y. that he hopes her new school will be pleasant, implores her to study and remember the Bible and its teachings and recalls his fondness for Steuben County. He also writes a note his sister Betsey about improvements made to Joseph Adams's carpets.
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Sarah and unnamed sister(s), 1858 Nov 20 (Folder 3)
        Charles writes to his daughters in New Haven asking them to return by train to Litchfield.
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Julia Hinman, 1862 Jun 1 (Folder 3)
        Charles writes to his wife their son, Frankie (Francis) has contracted scarlet fever and advises her to return home from Buffalo.
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Julia Hinman, 1863 June 16 (Folder 3)
        Charles writes from Washington, D.C. that he will be visiting with their son, Charlie. He reports on going to the Capitol and visiting with friends.
    - Adams, Charles, 1864-1870 (Folder 4)
      - Adams, Charles to unnamed daughter, 1864 Jun 7 (Folder 4)
        Charles writes that son Charlie has been badly wounded in the Civil War Battle of Cold Harbor. He lists the dead and wounded men from Litchfield.
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Julia Hinman and Wheelock, Mary Adams, 1864 Dec 11 (Folder 4)
        Charles writes to his wife that he is glad she had a good journey, describes how he misses the family members who usually sit around the dinner table, reports on family health and weather.
      - Adams, Charles to Adams, Julia Hinman, 1869 Apr 28 (Folder 4)
        Charles writes to his wife from Brooklyn, N.Y., that they are packing daughter Julia's effects and will return in several days. He reports on Julia and other visitors.
      - Adams, Charles to How, Julia Adams, 1870 Nov 15 (Folder 4)
        Charles writes to his daughter Julia from Brooklyn, N.Y., about the journey there with other daughters from Bath and plans for his return.
    - Kilbourn, Myron to Adams, Charles, 1864 Jul 23 (Folder 5)
      Kilbourn's letter accompanied the return of Charles Adams Jr.'s watch.
    - Lawrence, William R. to Adams, Charles, 1868 Feb. 11 (Folder 6)
      Lawrence, son of Amos Lawrence, writes about their common ancestor, Rev. Amos Adams (1728-1775). Enclosed is a letter to Lawrence from C. H. Dillaway, 1868 Feb 7.
    - [McMather?], D. to Adams, Charles, 1877 Mar 8 (Folder 7)
      [McMather?], a longtime friend of Adams, writes about people and places they knew in Bath, N.Y.
    - Peck, Tracy to Adams, Charles, 1859 May 14 (Folder 8)
      Peck, who is married to Adams's aunt Sally Adams, acknowledges receipt for rent and is concerned that it is more than he can afford to pay. Peck would be glad to see Adams and his family and hopes to ride to Litchfield. Peck expects Litchfield will have much business before the legislature this session because South Farms is asking to be made into a town.
    - Rogers, Henry W. to Adams, Charles, 1859-1869 (Folder 9)
      Four letters from Henry W. Rogers, husband of Charles Adams's sister Kezia Adams. He writes of Charles's daughters in Buffalo and family and business matters.
    - Valentine to Adams, Charles, circa 1855 (Folder 10)
      Poem written by "Valentine" about Adams's poetry-writing ability.
    - Weare, Mary Rogers to Adams, Charles, 1862 Mar 13 (Folder 11)
      Weare writes about her present situation in Cedar Rapids and family news.
    - Wessells, Leverett W. to Adams, Charles, 1862 (Folder 12)
      Wessells writes from Alexandria, Va., to his friend Adams about details of his encampment during the Civil War. The health of the soldiers, including Adams's son Charles, is good, their behavior is excellent, and he is eager to go to battle. He asks Adams to look into the matter of courts taxing is attendance at courts.
    - [?], Ellena, 1876 (Folder 13)
      Two letters written by Ellena to her guardian, Adams. She explains why she is in New York and asks for money with which to purchase a new winter outfit. She thanks him for the draft and describes her activities including attending a concert and news from friends and relatives.
  - Adams, Charles (1845-1864)
    Charles Adams (1845-1864) was the son of Charles and Julia Hinman Adams and grandson of Joseph and Deborah Marsh Adams. He was born in Litchfield. When the Civil War broke out, he enlisted in the 19th Regiment Connecticut Volunteers in 1862. On June 11, 1864, he died of wounds received on June 1 during the Battle of Cold Harbor. During the war, Adams regularly wrote letters to his parents and sisters. He recorded his thoughts about Generals McClellan, Burnside, and Grant, and President Lincoln; life in camp (maintaining and outfitting tents, sleeping arrangements, food, prayer meetings, entertainments and lectures, snowball battles); support for the Emancipation Proclamation; his belief in the cause; postings, guard duty, inspections, and drills; encouraging enlistment; speculation about duration of war and upcoming military activities; his cousin, Charles Hinman Graves, and other relatives he sees; the 40th N.Y. and Bull Run; African-American dock and government stores workers; guarding “contrabands” (freed or former slaves) from Virginia and Maryland; news of other Litchfield residents; politics in Connecticut; and the weather.
    - Adams, Charles, 1860 (Folder 1)
      Four letters to Adams's father, mother, and sisters Mary and Sarah describing going to school, church, and other childhood activities and interests.
    - Adams, Charles, 1861 (Folder 2)
      Two draft letters, one to Adams's mother and one to his cousin in Latin, in which he discuss the weather and going to church.
    - Adams, Charles, 1862 Aug-Sep (Folder 3)
      Four Civil War letters written in Alexandria, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1862 Oct (Folder 4)
      Five Civil War letters written in camp near Alexandria, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1862 Nov (Folder 5)
      Four Civil War letters written in camp near Alexandria, Va. and Alexandria.
    - Adams, Charles, 1862 Dec (Folder 6)
    - Adams, Charles, 1863 Jan (Folder 7)
      Four Civil War letters written in camp near Alexandria, Va. and Head Quarters near Fort Worth, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1863 Feb (Folder 8)
      Two Civil War letters written in Head Quarters near Fort Worth, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1863 Mar (Folder 9)
      Three Civil War letters written at Head Quarters of General Tyler.
    - Adams, Charles, 1863 Apr (Folder 10)
      Two Civil War letters written at Head Quarters of General Tyler.
    - Adams, Charles, 1863 May (Folder 11)
      Three Civil War letters written in Arlington House, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1863 Jun (Folder 12)
      Two Civil War letters written in Arlington House, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1863 Nov (Folder 13)
      Three Civil War letters written at Knight General Hospital, New Haven.
    - Adams, Charles, 1863 Dec (Folder 14)
      Three Civil War letters written at Bedloe's Island, New York, and Fort Worth, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1864 Jan (Folder 15)
      Three Civil War letters written at Fort Worth, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1864 Feb (Folder 16)
      Four Civil War letters written at Fort Worth, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1864 Mar (Folder 17)
    - Adams, Charles, 1864 Apr (Folder 18)
      Five Civil War letters written at Fort Worth, Va.
    - Adams, Charles, 1864 May (Folder 19)
      Two Civil War letters, one written at Fort Worth, Va., the other at Fort Craig, Va.
    - Gilbert, S. B. to relatives of Charles Adams Jr., 1864 Jun 15 (Folder 20)
      Solicitation card from S. B. Gilbert, notary public, general claim agent, "collects pensions, bounties, and back pay, due families or relatives of deceased officers or soldiers."
    - Rogers, Henry to relatives of Charles Adams Jr., circa 1864 Jun 15 (Folder 21)